Guide to the Henry Davies Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Henry Davies Papers
1888-1933
RG 85
Yale University Divinity School Library
3
(7 boxes)
Notes and writings document Davies' education and work. Henry Davies (1864-1940), was first a Congregational minister and later an Episcopal minister, primarily in Connecticut and Maryland. He was a lecturer on the History of Philosophy at Yale from 1896 to 1904.
Davies, Henry
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
1864 Jul 11 Born in London, England
1886 Completed studies at Cheshunt College, Cambridge, England
1888 B.D., Yale Divinity School
1888 Dec 5 Ordained as Congregational minister
1888-1890 Pastorate in Red Jacket, Michigan
1890-1898 Pastorates in Greens Farms, Derby, Rocky Hill, and Storrs, Connecticut
1896 Ph.D., Yale University
1896-1900 Lecturer on the History of Philosophy, Yale
1900-1904 Lecturer on the History of Philosophy and Aesthetics, Yale
1903 Nov 8 Ordained as an Episcopal minister
1903-1907 Pastorate in Salisbury, Connecticut
1907-1922 Pastorate in Easton, Maryland
1922-? Pastorate in Collingdale, Pennsylvania
1940 Died
Scope and Contents
I. Correspondence, 1899-1933.
II. Writings and Notes, 1886-1933.
There is just one folder of correspondence in this collection. The remainder of the material is notes, sermons, and writings of Davies. The class notes taken while studying for his B.D. and Ph.D. at Yaleare a valuable source of information regarding the curriculum and methods of teaching at Yale during the period 1886 to 1896. Courses taken by Davies dealt primarily with philosophy, psychology, and theology. His professors included Ladd, Duncan, and Sneath. One of the notebooks compiled by Davies while a Congregational minister deals sketchily with public school conditions in Connecticut.
Davies complemented his clerical duties by delivering lectures before various clubs and organizations. These lecture notes are arranged chronologically with topics noted on the folders. Typical topics include: "The Life and Poetry of Browning", "Evolution", and "Religion and Health". Also included among Davies' writings is a publsihed book, a manuscript draft of another book, and articles written for the Christian World in 1933.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1899-1933
II. Writings and Notes, 1886-1933
Clergy -- Connecticut; Clergy -- Maryland; Clergy; Davies, Henry
- Correspondence, 1899-1933; Series I
  - Chronologically arranged correspondence, 1899-1933 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Writings and Notes, Series II
  - Class notes while student at Yale
    - New Testament (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Psychology (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Theory of Knowledge (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Philosophical Anthropology (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Kant (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - History of Ethics (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Advanced Psychology (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Introduction to Philosophy (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Systematic Theology (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Philosophical Criticism (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Philosophical Sytems (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - History of Philosophy (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Human Intellect (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Pastoral Theology (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Notebooks kept as Congregational minister
    - Conditions of public school in North Mansfield, CT, 1888 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Notebook, 1892-1896 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Notebook, 1897-1919 (Box 8, Folder 42)
  - Lecture notes while instructor at Yale.
    - Topics include:"Pantheism and the Theory of Knowledge", etc., 1899-1903 (Box 3, Folder 13-17)
    - Topics include:"Physiological Aesthetics", etc. (Box 4, Folder 18-22)
  - Miscellaneous lecture notes
    - Chronologically arranged (boxes 5 and 6), 1909-1930 (Box 5, Folder 23-35)
    - Chronologically arranged (boxes 5 and 6) (Box 6)
  - Sermons
    - Chronologically arranged, 1888-1922 (Box 7, Folder 36-38)
  - Other writings
    - Art in Education and Life: book published by Davies, 1914 (Box 7, Folder 39)
    - "Humanism and Religion": manuscript book draft, 1924 (Box 7, Folder 40)
    - Manuscripts of articles written for the Christian World, 1933 (Box 7, Folder 41)